TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
（カルボ）生きていた
She's alive...
Episode 13
Neither
Human
nor
Tiger
Put the unburned firewood
next to the stove.
（バルサ）
燃え残りは 釜土の脇に移しときな
All right.
（チャグム）分かった
（ガキ大将）おーい！ おばさん
Hey! Lady!
この手紙 武人から預かった
（バルサ）武人？
A warrior told me
to give this letter to you!
A warrior?
（チャグム）おはよう
Good morning.
（ガキ大将）
よ… よう 昨日は すごかったな
Hey. You were really
amazing yesterday!
（チャグム）
えっ そうかな？ たまたまだよ
Um, you think so? lt was just luck.
Listen, who taught you that move?
Don't tell me it was...
（ガキ大将）なあ あの戦法―
いったい 誰に教わったんだよ？
おばさんか？
何て書いてあった？
What did the letter say?
ls it a challenge from somebody
who saw the match last night?
ゆうべの相撲を見たヤツからの
挑戦状か？
そんなところさ
Something like that.
Chagum! Pack your
things right away.
チャグム すぐ支度しな
出かける用事ができた
Something's come up,
and we have to leave.
Are you going to be all right?
（タンダ）大丈夫なのか？
（バルサ）つけられた気配はない
l didn't sense anyone following us.
That's not what l meant.
（タンダ）そうじゃなくて
手紙の文言から見て―
What l'm saying is that...
話して分かるような相手とは
思えないって言ってるんだ
...judging by his choice of words, it
doesn't sound like you can reason with him.
l agree. Looks like we were
spotted by the wrong person.
そうだな
やっかいなヤツに見られたもんさ
何者なんだ？ このカルボって武人
Who is he, anyway?
Who's this warrior named Karbo?
いわゆる商売敵ってやつでね
l guess you could
call him a business rival.
When l rescued a client
from slavers three years ago...
３年前 人買いから
依頼人を救い出したとき―
...he was a bodyguard
working for the other side.
敵側にいた用心棒だ
（タンダ）このまま ここに身を
隠すって手もあるんじゃないのか？
Can't you lay low here with Chagum?
l want to keep living at the
water mill until Torogai returns.
（バルサ）トロガイ師が戻るまでは
水車小屋で暮らしたいんだ
私が行かなきゃ
宮に ばらすと書いてある以上―
But if l don't meet him,
he's going to expose me to the court...
しかたあるまい
...so l have no choice.
ここで見つかっちまったら
元も子もないからね
lf we get spotted here,
it will all have been for nothing.
素性を知ってるヤツを
このままには しておけないよ
l can't let someone who
knows my identity run loose.
He might have realized
that Chagum is alive too.
チャグムのことも
気づいたかもしれないしね
殺さずの誓いを立てた身だ
なんとか 殺生は避けるよ
l gave my word that
l wouldn't take another life.
l'll find a way to avoid killing him.
Look after Chagum.
チャグムを頼む
（チャグム）俺が
祭りになんか行ったばっかりに…
This is all because
l went to the festival...
Don't worry about it. This was
bound to happen sooner or later.
（タンダ）気にすんな
遅かれ早かれ
こういうことは起こったんだ
バルサだって承知のはずさ
l'm sure that Balsa
realizes that too.
ゆうべ 死人が
ルチャをやっていたのは―
So, l guess l wasn't
seeing things when l saw...
...a dead woman in
a lucha match last night.
幻ではなかったようだな
What happened to
your Yogo sword?
（バルサ）ヨゴ刀は どうした？
（カルボ）捨てた
l gave it up.
Ever since our last meeting...
あれ以来 ずっと
こいつで お前を斬ると決めていた
...l promised myself that
l was going to kill you using this.
すまないが
私と会ったことは忘れてくれ
l'm sorry, but you'll have
to forget that you saw me.
あのときの屈辱を晴らすのが目的だ
l mean to make you
pay for humiliating me!
嫌でも つきあってもらうぞ
Like it or not,
you are going to fight me.
l've been waiting a long time
for this day to arrive.
この日をずっと待っていた
お前を斬ることだけを夢想し
山狩り隊にも加わった
All l could think about was killing you,
so l even took part in that manhunt.
Granted, you did ambush me...
あのとき
奇襲をかけられたとはいえ―
ぶざまに負けた俺を
お前は なぜ 斬らずに去った？
...but why did you leave me dishonored
and defeated without finishing me off?
さあね
Who's to say?
あの連れ子 第二皇子だな
（バルサ）あっ…
That boy who was with you.
He's the second prince, isn't he?
うん？ いいぞ その目だ
Good, that's the look
l wanted to see.
Tomorrow morning, be at
the Tonan highway barrier.
明朝 都南街道(となんかいどう)の関門前に立て
（バルサ）しつこいね 私は…
You don't know when
to give up, do you? l...
Whether or not you come to
the barrier is entirely your choice.
来る来ないは お前の自由だ
But know that l will follow the first traveler
who leaves the barrier after sunrise...
ただし 日が昇って
最初に街道を行く旅人を１人―
...and kill him.
斬る
お前が来るまで
それが 毎日 続くことになる
And l will do this every morning
until you do decide to show up.
The only way to stop me
is for you to kill me yourself.
やめさせたければ
俺を斬る以外ない
他人のために振るった剣に―
The humiliation of
a sword wielded for oneself...
己のための剣が破れた屈辱
...being defeated by a sword
wielded in the service of another...
お前を斬って 過去を精算する
l will settle the past by killing you.
そうしないと
どれだけ修業を積んでも―
lf l don't, my spirit will never
be able to put this behind me...
...no matter how much
l train and discipline myself.
心が前に進まんのだ
生きていたことに感謝する
l am grateful to you for being alive.
（タンドル）
あっ… こら！ どうした？
Hey! W-What's gotten into you!
Whoa! Whoa, now!
（バルサ）どう！ どう！
（タンドル）ハッ…
あっ… 先生！
S-Sensei!
Thank you so much.
l'm not used to handling horses...
（セーナ）ありがとうございます
（セーナ）馬の扱いには
慣れていないものですから
しかたないよ
ああなっちゃ 素人には無理さ
lt couldn't be helped. A horse gone
wild can't be reined in by a novice.
Sensei! l'm so sorry!
Are you all right?
（タンドル）
先生 すいません 大丈夫ですか？
Yes...
（タンドル）ふだんは
おとなしい馬なんですが…
Normally, she's such a docile horse...
あっ… どうも 助かりました
Thank you for helping us.
おかしいな
なんで 急に暴れたりしたんだ？
That's strange, why'd you
go wild all of a sudden?
どうどう！ ほら 何でもないだろ？
Come on, there's nothing out there.
You hired a stone shooter, l see.
Just like the last time...
（バルサ）
礫者(つぶてもの)を雇ったね あのときと同じか
l-l think we should go.
い… 行きましょう
ずっと ついてきますね
She's been following us
ever since the gate...
南へは
この道一本きりだからでしょ
Most likely because this is
the only road leading south.
lt bothers me that her short spear is just
like the one the warrior on that rock had.
（タンドル）
でも あの岩の上の武人と―
同じ短槍(たんそう)を持っているのが
気になりましてね
Let's take a break there then.
では あそこで 一息 入れましょう
どちらまで行かれるのですか？
And where might
you be traveling to?
あなたたちは？
How about yourselves?
南端の漁村まで行く予定です
Our plan is to go to a fishing village
at the southern tip of the mainland.
What a coincidence.
（バルサ）私もです
うわっ！ 何だ？ こりゃ
What in the world!
Who would do something like this?
誰が こんなことを…
Why don't you come
closer to the fire?
もう少し
火のほうに来てはいかがです？
（バルサ）気にしないでください
慣れてますから
Don't worry about me.
l'm used to the cold.
あなたも 南の漁村に行くと
おっしゃっていたけれど―
You mentioned that you are
also traveling to the fishing village.
あちらには どういった ご用で？
Might l ask what takes you there?
（バルサ）ちょっと やぼ用で
（セーナ）そうですか
Just an errand.
Ah, l see.
As for me, l have been hired to teach
the children there how to read and write.
私は 子供たちに 読み書きを
教えに行くことになりましたの
へえ 先生ですか
立派な仕事ですね
Oh, you're a teacher?
That's a fine profession.
You seem to be
from another country.
異国の方のようですね
（バルサ）はい そうです
Yes. That's right.
あなたは どんな仕事を？
And what sort of work do you do?
l am no expert on the subject
of swords and spears...
私 剣や槍(やり)に
詳しくないのですが―
...but you wouldn't happen to be
a Kanbal warrior, would you?
あなたは
もしや カンバルの武人ですか？
Warrior makes it sound
more glamorous than it really is.
武人と言えば
聞こえはいいですが―
まあ ただの用心棒ってやつです
l'm just a bodyguard, nothing more.
女の用心棒…
それは大変なお仕事ですね
A female bodyguard?
That must be a difficult line of work.
まあ
l suppose.
用心棒といえど 武人は武人
You say you are a bodyguard,
but a warrior is a warrior.
なら ヨゴに伝わる
虎になった武人の話をご存じ？
That being the case,
do you know the Yogo tale called...
..."The Warrior who
Became a Tiger"?
いいえ
No, l don't.
lt's a fable about a warrior
who devoted his entire life...
（セーナ）生涯を―
剣の腕を上げることだけに
費やした武人の ぐう話です
...to training to increase
his skill with his sword.
So obsessed was
this warrior with power...
その武人は
強さに こだわるあまり―
...that in hopes of
becoming as strong as a tiger...
虎のようになりたいと思い―
虎の毛皮をまとって
戦いを続けていました
...he took to fighting
while clad in a tiger's hide.
The warrior's plan worked...
そのかいあって 武人は
やがて どこにも敵がいなくなった
...and in due time, there
were no more enemies to fight.
But one day, he realized that he had,
in fact, turned into a real tiger.
けれど あるとき 自分が―
本当の虎になっていることに
気づいたのです
それで？
And then what?
And then the warrior,
who had lost the ability to speak...
（セーナ）そして 言葉も
なくしてしまった武人は―
最後は 家族も友人も失い
独り寂しく竹林の中で生涯を送った
...eventually lost
his family and friends...
...and lived out his days
alone in a bamboo grove.
失礼ですが あなたからは―
You'll have to forgive me, but
even an untrained eye such as mine...
素人の私にも分かるほどの
殺気が感じられるのです
...can detect an air of
menace coming from you.
それで
こんな話をしてしまいました
That is why l told you that story.
You can, can you? l suppose
l still need some more training.
そうですか
まだまだ
修業が足りなかったようです
失礼します
lf you'll excuse me...
さすがは先生だ
l knew you could do it, Sensei!
あんな おっかねえ武人を
怒らせずに追い出すなんて
You managed to send that dreadful
warrior away without angering her!
You misunderstand. l didn't
tell her that story to drive her away.
違うの
私は あの人を追い出すために
この話をしたのではないの
On the contrary, l was curious about
why she has such a thirst for blood...
むしろ なぜ あんなに
殺気だっているのかが不思議で
...and had hoped to ask her why.
その訳を聞こうと思っていたのよ
You're a strange one, Sensei.
先生は変わってるなあ
俺は 昼間っから あの女が
おっかなくてしかたなかったのに
l've been scared to death of that
woman ever since this afternoon.
This should keep the rain off.
（バルサ）雨は しのげるか
A stone shooter and dead rats...
礫者に ねずみの死骸
そして 今度は眠らせない作戦か
And now his plan is
to keep me from sleeping, huh?
You're planning to come after me using
exactly the same tactics l used on you...
私がやったのと
まったく同じ方法で やる気だね
このまま
つきあうほかないってことか
Apparently, l have no choice
but to play along with him.
Nothing fazes this lady, does it?
（ギョプサル）
あの女 えらく腹が据わってますね
My shots are grazing her cheek,
but she hasn't so much as blinked.
（ギョプサル）顔をかすめてるのに
まばたき一つ しやがらねえ
一発 額にでも当ててやりますか
Shall l fire one
right into her forehead?
Do only as you're told.
（カルボ）余計なことをするな
Who is she, anyway?
何者なんです？ あいつ
（カルボ）お前が知る必要はない
You don't need to know.
Suffice it to say that she's the
only opponent l've ever failed to kill.
だが ヤツは
唯一 俺が斬り損ねた相手だ
そうでなくては困る
l wouldn't have this any other way.
Keep her awake by firing stones
at her at random intervals.
時折 礫を混ぜて 一睡もさせるな
lf she moves, move with her.
Keep it up all night.
場所を変えたら
お前も移動して 一晩中 続けるんだ
小屋に入ったら
小屋の屋根や壁にぶつけてやれ
lf she goes inside the hut,
fire your stones into the roof or walls.
ただし
あいつが襲ってきたら すぐ逃げろ
But if she attacks you,
you're to clear out right away.
間違っても殺してはならん
Under no circumstances
are you to kill her. ls that clear?
分かったな？
（ギョプサル）へい
Yes, sir!
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
（タンドル）あの雨だ
さすがに先に行っちまったか
Well, it was raining hard,
so l guess she went on ahead.
（セーナ）上がりましたね
（タンドル）ええ
l see that it's stopped raining.
Yes.
And it looks like that
woman has left too.
あの女も行っちまったようです
これで 一安心だ
l think we can relax now.
（バルサ）
悪いが 今日も同行させてもらうよ
l'm sorry, but l'll be
accompanying you again today.
ゆうべは
どちらで お休みになったの？
Where did you sleep last night?
一睡も
（タンドル）えっ
l didn't.
Then you should have
just gone on ahead!
なら さっさと行きゃいいんだ！
なんで わざわざ待ってるんだ？
Why did you wait around for us?
あんた 薄気味悪いんだよ
There's something creepy about you!
There's no need
to take that tone of voice.
そんなふうに
言うもんじゃありません
（タンドル）だって…
（バルサ）かまわないよ
But she's...
l don't mind.
But there's a very good reason
why l have to stay close to you two.
だけど どうしても―
あんたらと離れるわけには
いかない事情があってね
That's ridiculous.
We don't want you around!
冗談じゃねえ！
こっちが ごめんだぜ！
l know it's against the rules for the
packhorse driver to ride with the client...
先生 馬方が一緒に乗ることは
ご法度ですが―
...but please bear with me until
we can get away from this woman!
こいつを まくまで
辛抱してくだせえ ハッ！
待て！ 私から離れると…
Wait! lf you leave my side, you'll...
（バルサ）大丈夫か？
Are you all right?
（タンドル）寄るな！
Stay away!
He leaves me no choice...
しかたないね
The truth is, l've gotten
you two involved in my affairs...
実は あんたらを
私の事情に巻き込んじまってね
関門を抜けたとき
岩の上に武人がいたろ？
When you left the barrier gate, you
saw a warrior standing on a rock, right?
もし あのとき
私が引き返していたら―
lf l had turned back,
he was going to kill one of you.
あいつは あんたら２人のうちの
どちらかを―
斬り殺すつもりだったんだ
私は あいつに
剣の勝負を申し込まれていてね
This man challenged me
to a sword fight, you see.
When l refused...
私が断ると あいつは―
...he said he would kill the first person
to pass through the gate each day.
“その日１番に関門を通る人間を
１人ずつ斬り殺す”と言ってきた
（セーナ）では
もし あなたが いなかったら…
Then if you had not been there...
たぶん
あんたか馬方が斬られただろう
Either you or your packhorse driver
would have been killed.
l-l don't believe this!
（タンドル）じ… 冗談じゃねえ
それでも 私は ある事情から―
The problem is, for various reasons,
l've sworn to never take another life.
もう二度と 人を斬ることは
しないと誓ったもんだから―
l had hoped to find a way
to avoid fighting him...
なんとしても勝負を断り―
他人を巻き込むことも
やめさせようと思ったんだ
...while also keeping him from
involving innocent bystanders.
But it looks like he isn't
going to listen to reason.
でも あいつには
そんな道理は通じないらしい
ふざけるな！
Are you out of your mind?
どんな事情か知らねえが
斬り合いが嫌なら自分が斬られろ！
l don't care what your reasons are!
lf you don't want to fight,
go let him kill you!
Just leave other people out of it!
そんなことに
他人様を巻き込むんじゃねえ！
l agree. But l can't afford
to be killed just yet.
そのとおりだね
でも 私も まだ
斬られるわけには いかないんだよ
Karbo! l know you're
out there listening!
カルボ！ そこで聞いてるんだろ！
（カルボ）お前が やったように
３日３晩 眠らせず―
Just as you did to me, l was
going to attack after trailing you...
...for three days and
nights with no sleep.
さんざん つけ回してから
仕掛けようと思っていたが―
But if this is the way
you want it, l'll oblige you.
お前が その気なら かまわない
ここで思いの丈を晴らさせてもらう
l'm going to unburden myself
right here and now!
（バルサ）行きな！
もう あいつは あんたらに用はない
Get going! He doesn't have
any more use for you two.
（タンドル）さ… さあ
Come on!
Those two are my shooter's reward.
あいつらは 礫者の駄賃だ
Enough is enough!
いいかげんにしろ！
l'm the one you're fighting!
Pay attention to nothing but me!
貴様の相手は この俺だ！
俺だけを見ろ！
うら！
（カルボ）ああっ！
l guess l have no choice
but to become a tiger...
どうやら
虎になるほかないようだ
いいぞ！
That's more like it!
Now you'll be worth killing!
それでこそ斬りがいがある！
（ギョプサル）待った 待った！
Wait! Wait a minute!
You two are my reward!
お前らは 俺の駄賃だ
l won't force you
to strip down or anything.
身ぐるみ剥ぐとは言わねえ
有り金全部 置いていきな！
Put down all your money and go!
お前もだ！
You too!
やった…
l got him...
Come on, Sensei,
let's get out of here.
先生 早く逃げましょう
Not yet, we have to
stop that woman.
待って あの人を止めなければ
はあ？ 何言ってんですか？
What are you talking about?
殺し合いなんか
勝手に やらせとけばいいんですよ
We should just let
those two kill each other!
関係ねえもんを巻き込みやがって
ちくしょう！
Dragging us into their mess
when we had nothing to with it...
Damn it!
Nothing to do with it?
関係ない？ そうでしょうか？
Are you so sure about that?
That woman secretly acted as
our bodyguard and kept us safe.
あの方は 私たちのために―
黙って 用心棒を
引き受けてくれていたのですよ
そんな！
あれは 勝手に あいつが…
Come on! lt's not
like we asked her to...
We mustn't allow her
to turn into a tiger!
あの方を虎にさせてはなりません！
あっ… 先生！
Sensei!
Let me tell you the reason
why l didn't kill you that day.
（バルサ）なぜ あのとき
お前を斬らなかったか教えてやろう
私は奪ってしまった命と
同じ数だけ―
l had sworn to save the same
number of lives that l had taken.
人を救おうと誓っていた
だが命の重さが
全て平等ってことは―
But by the time l fought you,
l had already realized that all lives...
...weren't of equal value.
あのとき すでに悟っていた
だから 人を助ける度に―
That's why l was sick of killing
insignificant scum like you...
お前みたいな
ちっぽけな男を斬るのが―
...every time l saved
someone else's life.
ばかばかしくなったのさ！
ちっぽけだと？
lnsignificant scum?
だが 私には まだ
やらなきゃいけないことがあるんだ
But there's still something that
l need to see through to the end!
邪魔するヤツは…
And whoever gets in my way...
Who are you calling
insignificant scum?
（カルボ）ちっぽけだと？
俺が… この俺が ちっぽけだと！
How dare you...
How dare you call me insignificant!
うらー！
Sensei, please!
（タンドル）先生ってば！
あっ… 先生！
Sensei!
（セーナ）いけない！
その人を斬ってはいけません！
You mustn't!
You mustn't kill that man!
What have you done...
なんてことを…
Why did you...
あなた なぜ…
（バルサ）うるせえ！
Shut your mouth! l'm a tiger!
私は虎だ！ 近寄ると食い殺すぞ！
Don't come near me
or l'll rip you apart!
俺は なんて ちっぽけなんだ
l'm insignificant...
先生 いったい全体 こりゃ…
Sensei, what in the world
just happened here?
l have no idea. l could have sworn
that she struck this man down.
分からない
確かに
あの女人は この男を斬ったはず
俺など目に入っていなかった
This whole time,
l was beneath her notice...
お願い！ あの人を呼んできて！
（タンドル）あっ…
Please! Go call her back!
She thinks that she killed this man!
今 あの女人は
この人を斬ったと思い込んでいる
But the truth is she didn't!
でも 本当は斬っていなかった
そのことを
伝えてあげなければ あの人は…
lf we don't tell her that
he's still alive, she's going to...
l-l'm on my way!
あっ… 分かりました
You there. Do you know
what that woman's name is?
あなた あの女人の名前をご存じ？
l don't know.
知らぬ
No, l've forgotten it...
いや 忘れてしまった
（タンドル）おーい！
Hey!
おーい！
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
With no regard to their own safety,
two sages make discoveries.
One, a long-buried history.
The other, a hidden conspiracy.
Next time,
"The Knot."
Episode 14
The Knot
Look around you! What the
world needs now is this truth!